<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A goodly exposition vpon the xxx. psalme In te domine speraui</title>
            <author>Savonarola, Girolamo, 1452-1498.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21798.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3992</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">34382680</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 34382680</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29051</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11549)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29051)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1904:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A goodly exposition vpon the xxx. psalme In te domine speraui</title>
                  <author>Savonarola, Girolamo, 1452-1498.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Byddell for W. Marshall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Translation of meditation of Savonarola--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-c⁴, d².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Pepys Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXX --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29051:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Be it knowen to al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>entes, that it is prohibited by o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the kynge, by his letters p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ers, boke ſellers, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers that (with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ym, that at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es printe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> nexte th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey wyll anſwere at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yde the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties mentioned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> unto graunted.</p>
            <p>¶Imprynted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leteſtrete by Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bydd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the ſigne of the Sor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cundite / for wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> / the yere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29051:1"/>
            <head>¶A goodly expoſition vpon the .xxx. pſalme In te domine ſpetaui.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Euynes hath beſeged me with a greate and ſtronge hooſte ſhe hath encloſed me, ſhe hath oppreſſed my hert w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> clamours and ceaſſeth not with weapons nyghte and day to fyghte agaynſt me.</p>
            <p>My frendes be in her tentes, and are become myn ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. what ſoeuer I ſe, what ſoeuer I heare, brynge the banners of heuines, the memorie of my frendꝭ ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me ſadde, the recordynge of my chyldren greueth me, the conſyderyng of my cloyſter and cell vexeth me, the reuoluynge of my ſtudies maketh me penſyfe, the thynkyng of my ſynnes oppreſſeth me. For lyke as to them, whiche be ſycke of the axeſſe, all ſwete thynges ſeme bytter, ſo to me all thynges be turned in to ſorowe and heuynes. Vndoubtedly a great burthen vpon the herte is this heuynes. The venyme of a deadly peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence grudgeth agaynſte god, ſeaſeth not to blaſpheme and exhorteth to deſperation. Oh vnhappy man that I am, who ſhall delyuer me from her curſed handes? If all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſe and heare folowe her banners and fyghte agaynſt me, who ſhalbe my ꝓtectour? who ſhall helpe me? whyther ſhall I go? whyther ſhall I flee? I wote what I ſhall do, I wyll turne me to thynges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, &amp; brynge them agaynſt the viſible. And who ſhall be the guyde of ſo hyghe and terrible an hooſte? Hope, whiche is of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges inuiſible. Hope, I ſay, ſhall come agaynſt heuines, and vaynquyſhe her. who can ſtande agaynſt hope? Heare what the prophete ſayth: Thou arte (lorde) my hope, thou haſte ſet thy refuge moſte hygh. who ſhall ſtande agaynſt the lorde? who
<pb facs="tcp:29051:2"/> can wynne his towre of refuge, whiche is moſt hygh? wherfore I wyll call her, doubtles ſhe wyll come, nor ſhe wyll not confoundeme. Lo nowe ſhe commeth, ſhe hath broughte gladnes, ſhe hath taughte me to fyghte. &amp; ſhe ſayd to me, Crye, ceaſe not. And I ſayde, what ſhall I crye? Crye, quod ſhe, boldely and with all thy whole herte, ſay:
<q>In te domine ſperaui non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>funder in eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>num / et in iuſtitia tua libera me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ That is to ſaye: In the oh lorde, I haue truſted, I ſhall not be confounded for euermore, and in thy iuſtice delyuer me.</p>
            <p>¶ Oh the wonderful power of hope, whoſe face heui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes can not abyde. Nowe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth conforte. Let heuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes cry nowe and ſtruggle agay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt me with her armie. Let the worlde thruſt downe, let the enemies make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, I feare nothynge, for I truſt (lorde) in the, for thou arte my hope, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte put my refuge moſte hygh. I haue alredy entered it, hope hath led me in, I my ſelfe entered not vnſhamefaſtly, ſhe ſhall excuſe me before the. Beholde, ꝙ hope, o man the moſte hygh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge of god, open thyn iyes, and ſe, it is god alone, it is onely he, an infinite ſee of ſubſtaunce. Other thinges ſo be, as though they were not. For all thingꝭ depende of hym, and oneleſſe he ſuſtayned them, they ſhulde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deynly retourne to noughte, for of noughte were they made. Conſydre the power of hym, whiche in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng created heuen &amp; earthe. Doth not he worke all in all thynges? who can moue his hande without hym? who can thynke any thynge of hym ſelfe?</p>
            <p>Ponder his wyſedome, whiche in tranquilitie gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all, for he ſeeth all, and to his iyes all thynges be
<pb facs="tcp:29051:2"/> naked and open. This is he, whiche onely knowethe howe to delyuer the, and onely can conforte &amp; ſaue the. Put not thy truſte in the chyldren of men, in whom is no ſaluation. The herte of men is in his power, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer he luſteth, he wyll turne it. This is he, whiche may &amp; can helpe the. Doeſt thou ſuſpecte his wyll? Ponder his goodnes, conſydre his tender loue. Is not he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> louer of men, which for men became man, and for ſynners was crucified? This is thy trewe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whiche created the, whiche redemed the, which alwayes hath done good vnto the. Can the father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his ſonne? Caſte thy ſelfe on hym, &amp; he wyll take the vp and ſaue the. Serche the ſcriptures, and thou ſhalte fynde howe buſely his great tender loue moueth the to truſte in hym. And why dothe he that? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bicauſe he coueteth to ſaue. For what ſaythe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ꝓphete. Bicauſe he truſted in me, I wyl deliuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lo, for none other cauſe he wyll delyuer hym, but bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he truſted in hym. And what other thyng hath the prophetes, the apoſtles, yea he hym ſelfe, the lorde of the apoſtles preached, but that men ſhulde truſte in the lorde? Sacrifice therfore (ye men) the ſacrifice of iuſtice, and truſte in the lorde, and he ſhall delyuer you, and plucke you out of all tribulation. Oh the greate vertue of hope, truely ſhe is ſpred abrode. For grace is ſpred abrode in her lyppes. Oh this is truely thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, ſo hygh (good lorde) to whiche the euyll of heuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes can not approche. This I knewe and vnderſtode, therfore I truſted lorde in the. For though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weight of ſyn dothe greuouſly preſſe me, yet I can not deſpaire / for thy goodnes ſo gently prouoked me to hope, that I can not be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for euermore. For a tyme I may
<pb facs="tcp:29051:3"/> well be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, but for euermore ſurely I can not. For hope, whiche hath ledde me in to thy moſte hyghe refuge hath taught me to hope, not temporall thyngꝭ, but euerlaſtynge. For hope is of thynges inuiſible.</p>
            <p>But tho thynges that be ſene, are temporall. And the thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that be not ſene, are euerlaſtyng. wherfore I hearyng the wordes of hope, whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to plucke me out from the handes of heuines, haue truſted lorde in the, couetyng before all thyngꝭ to be delyuered from my ſynnes, and thrugh thy mercy and grace to come to thynges euerlaſtynge, whiche be inuiſible. This is my fyrſte and chiefe deſyre, for my ſynnes be a greate tribulation vnto me. For from this all other tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion iſſueth. Take awaye lorde my ſynnes, and I am free from all tribulation. For tribulation &amp; penſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes of mynde, procede from the fountayn of the herte. For euery heuynes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of loue. If I loue my ſonne, and he dyeth, I am troubled bicauſe I haue loſte that I loued. If I loue not my ſeruaunt, and he dyeth, I am not heuy, bycauſe I haue loſte that I loued not.</p>
            <p>Take away therfore lord my ſinnes thrugh thy grace, what remayneth, but that I ſhall loue the with al my whole herte, &amp; deſpiſe all temporal thynges as vayne? If than I haue the by fayth, of whom alſo I hope to haue, that, whiche neither iye hath ſene, nor eare hath herde / nor hath not aſcended in to the herte of man.</p>
            <p>what thynge can trouble me? That, whiche I haue loſte beſyde god, I haue loſte that I loue not. In the oh lorde I haue truſted, lyke as my hope hath taught me to truſte / therfore I ſhall not be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for euer, for thou ſhalte gyue me euerlaſtynge thynges. who truſteth not in the, but in his owne vanitie, ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded
<pb facs="tcp:29051:3"/> for euermore. For he ſhall deſcende to eternall confuſion. I may be confounded temporally, bothe of the, &amp; of all men, but I ſhall not be confounded for euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>more. For of the I may be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, whyle I deſyre to be delyuered from temporal vexation, and perauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thou wylte not heare me. Truely than I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded temporally. For it is not expedient for me, ſith that vertue is made ꝑfecte in infirmitie. And of men I am temporally confounded, &amp; they preuayle agaynſt me, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they purſue me. But this alſo thou ſuffreſt them to do, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhulde not be confounded for euermore. wherfore, yf before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de yeres be but as yeſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day, whiche is paſſed away, I wyll gladly ſuffre tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſions, that I be not confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for euermore. I wyll truſte in the lorde, for hope hath taughte me to truſte, and ſhortely I ſhalbe delyuered from all tribula<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. By what merites ſhall I be delyuered? Not by myn, lord but by thy iuſtice deliuer me. By thy iuſtice I ſay not by min. I ſeke mercy, I offre not my iuſtice. But yf by thy grace thou wylte make me ryghtwyſe, nowe I haue thy iuſtice. For thy grace in vs is thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. The phariſees truſted in workes of iuſtice, they truſted in theyr owne iuſtice / and therfore they were not ſubiecte to the iuſtice of god. For of the workes of the lawe ſhall no creature be iuſtified with the. But the iuſtice of god appered by the grace of Ieſu Chriſt, yea w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the workes of the lawe. The philoſophers gloried in theyr iuſtice, and therfore they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de not thy iuſtice, bicauſe they entred not in at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dore. They were theues and robbers, whiche came not to ſaue, but to deſtroy and ſley the ſheepe. wherfore thy grace is thy iuſtice lorde, &amp; it were no lenger grace, yf it were giuen
<pb facs="tcp:29051:4"/> of the merites. wherfore not in my iuſtice, but in thy iuſtice delyuer me from my ſynnes, Or ſurely delyuer me in thy iuſtice, that is to wit, in thy ſonne, whiche onely amongeſt men is founde iuſte. what is thy ſon, but the very iuſtice, in whiche men be iuſtified? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in thy iuſtice iuſtifie me and delyuer me from my ſynnes, that I may be alſo delyuered from other affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, whiche I ſuffre therfore, ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe taken away, the effecte myghte alſo be taken away.</p>
            <p>Lo, the, oh lorde, haue I beſoughte, &amp; I am conforted, hope hath ſo taught me, I am replenyſhed with ioye, bicauſe I truſte in the, therfore I ſhall not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for euermore. Heuynes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth agayne with greate purueyaunce, ſhe is returned with ſwerdꝭ and ſperes on euery ſyde, ſhe is defended with greate violence, ſhe walketh, ſhe hath beſeged our citie. The crye of her horſemen hath feared me. Standynge without, ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded ſilence, and a farreof, ſhe ſpake, ſayenge: Oh, ꝙ ſhe, lo, yonder is he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truſted in the lorde, which ſayde, I ſhall not be confounded for euermore, whiche hath folowed hope, his confortatrice. And whan ſhe perceyued me at theſe wordꝭ to waxe aſhamed, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng me nyghe, ſhe ſayde, where be the promyſes of thy hope? where is the conforte? where is the delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce? what haue thy teares ꝓfited the? what haue thy prayers brought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> from heuen? Thou haſt cryed, and no man hath anſwered the, thou haſte wepte, and no man hath ben moued with pitie vpon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, thou haſte called vpon thy god, &amp; he holdeth his peace, thou haſte deſyred the helpe of the ſaintes, and none of them hath regarded the. Lo, what profite haue the wordes of hope brought the? Thou haſte laboured, and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> fyndeſt
<pb facs="tcp:29051:4"/> nothynge in thy handes. Thynkeſt thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the inhabitantes of the earthe? Nay he walketh aboute the limittes of heuen, and conſydereth not our maters. Thus ſhe blaſphemynge ſpake. And whan I ſhoke for feare at her wordes, approchyng, ſhe ſpake in myn eare, ſayenge: Troweſt thou tho thynges be trewe that faythe ſheweth? wylte thou ſe that they be but mennes fantaſies? Thou ſhalte knowe hereby.</p>
            <p>For if god became man (as they ſay) and was crucified for men, it coulde not be, but that ſo greate loue ſhulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte a man, neuer ſo moche oppreſſed with heuines, wepynge &amp; cryenge vnto hym, yf (as they ſay) infinite goodnes cauſed him to come downe from heuen to take vpon hym the croſſe, howe ſhulde he not nowe come downe to miſerable men, that he myght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte them? Surely this is more eaſie, and with lyke loue oughte to be holpen. why do not the angelles and ſayntes, yf they be ſo pitefull, come to conforte the? Howe many men troweſt thou, wolde, if they myghte, come to the? and with theyr wordes and workꝭ (as moche as they myght) wolde conforte the, whiche wolde alſo delyuer the from all vexation? why do not the ſayntes this, whiche are thoughte to be farre better than men?</p>
            <p>Beleue me, all thingꝭ are gouerned by caſualte. There be no thynges, but tho that be ſene, your ſpirite ſhall vaniſhe away like ſmoke. who euer came agayn from helle or heuen and tolde vs ſuche thynges as they ſaye do chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſoules after this lyfe? Theſe are but fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of folyſhe women. Aryſe therfore and flee to the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes helpe, that thou mayſt be loſened from priſon, and lyue in pleaſure, and not be deceyued falſely of this thy hope, and alwayes be in payne and trouble.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29051:5"/>
            <p>Theſe thynges ſayde, ſo greate crye was herde in her tentes, ſo greate dynne of the harneis, and noyſe of the trompettes, that vnneth I coulde ſtande on my feete. And yf my welbeloued hope had not the ſoner holpen, heuines had led me bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with chaines to her region. wherfore hope came ſhynynge with a certayne diuine bryghtnes, and ſmylyng, ſayd: O ſouldiour of Chriſt, what herte, what mynde haſte thou in this batayle? whiche I hearyng, forthwith was aſhamed. And ſhe ſayde, feare thou not, this euyll ſhall not take the, thou ſhalte not peryſhe, lo, I am with the to delyuer the.</p>
            <p>Knoweſt thou not that it is wryten, The vnwyſe man ſayd in his herte, there is no god. This heuines hath ſpoken lyke one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> folyſſhe women. Can ſhe ꝑſwade the that there is no god, or that god hath not the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of all thynges? Canſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doubte of fayth, whiche with ſo many argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and reaſons haſt confirmed it? I wonder that thou arte ſo felled to the grounde at her wordes. Tell me, I praye the, beganneſt thou to doubte in thy herte of faythe? O my ſwete mother, the lyuynge god is my witneſſe and alſo my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, that I felte no maner prycke of infidelitie, for by the grace of Chriſte, I beleue no leſſe tho thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to be true, whiche be appertaynyng to faythe, than tho thinges, whiche I beholde with my bodely iyes. But heuines ſo preſſed me, that rather I ſhulde haue ben broughte to diſperation than to infidelitie. Son, thou knoweſt that this is a greate gyfte of god, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not of workꝭ, that no man ſhulde glorie. Wherfore aryſe and feare not, but rather knowe hereby that the lorde hath not forſaken the, which although he heareth not forth with, ye oughte not deſpayre. If he make tariaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:29051:5"/> abyde hym, for he wyll ſurely come, and not carye.</p>
            <p>The ploughman abydeth pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the frute in the due tyme. Nature not forthwith gyueth the ꝑfecte ſhappe whan ſhe bryngeth forthe a thynge, but fyrſte ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth the mater, and diſpoſeth it by lytle and lytle, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll ſhe maketh it apte to receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhappe. Yet knowe thou that the lorde always heareth hym that prayeth deuoutely &amp; mekely, for they neuer departe voyde from hym. Nor I wyll not labour to proue this w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reaſons, bicauſe thou feleſt it in thy ſelfe. Tell me, who lyfted vppe thy herte to god? who induced the to praye? who made the to ſorowe for thy ſynnes, and to wepe? who gaue the hope? who made the cherefull in thy prayer, and after thy prayer? And alſo what is he that dayly confirmed the in thy holy purpoſe? Is it not the lorde, whiche worketh all in all thynges? Yf he than gyueth the continually theſe gyftes, why dothe that curſed woman ſaye, where be thy prayers? where be thy teares, &amp; the other wordꝭ of blaſphemie? Knoweſt thou not that the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Hieruſalem is diſtincted from this terreſtral? Knoweſt thou not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient nor neceſſarie, nor profitable, that god or his angelles ſhulde deſcende viſibly to men, and ſpeake familiarlye to them. Fyrſt it is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, ſo vnworthy be our merites. For howe can lyghte and darkenes agree?</p>
            <p>Diuerſe cities haue citezens of contrary and dyuerſe natures. Howe be it to ſome for theyr excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t holynes, for aſmoche as theyr lyfe was heuenly, it was graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſe angelles, and to ſpeke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. But a ſpeciall priuilege belongeth not to all. It is not neceſſarie, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that ſyth bleſſed angelles inuiſibly gouerne vs, illuminate &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte vs. It nedeth not to ſhewe viſible
<pb facs="tcp:29051:6"/> apparancies. Howe be it our lorde is ſo good, that alſo viſible viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whan he ſeeth nede, he doth not omitte. For what thynge myghte he haue done for our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hath not done it? Finally it is not profitable, for ouermoche familiaritie engendreth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempte. For to the Iues myracles both greate and many, nothyng auayled. For rare be precious. wherfore let the inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible viſitation ſuffice the / for the lorde knoweth what thou haſt nede of. Hath not he conforted the? I knowe what thou thynkeſt in thy herte. Aryſe than and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne to prayer. Crye, aſke, ſeke, ꝑſeuer / for yf he wyl not gyue bicauſe thou art his frende, yet for thy impor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tunitie he wyll gyue all that be neceſſarie. with theſe wordes conforted, I aroſe, and proſtrate before god, I proceded in my prayer, ſayenge:
<q>Inclina ad me aucem tuam acceleta vt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruas me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶That is to ſay. Bowe downe thyn eare vnto me, haſten the to plucke me out.</p>
            <p>¶Oh lorde my god, to the I returne, hope hath ſente me vnto the, I do not come by myn owne preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption.</p>
            <p>Thy goodnes prouoketh me, thy mercy draweth me.</p>
            <p>Oh howe greate a gentlenes is this? Surely I ioye in my herte / nor I deſire none other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation. Happy truely is this neceſſitie, which compelleth me to come vnto the, whiche conſtrayneth me to ſpeake with the, whiche forſeth me to praye. wherfore I ſpeake to my god, though I be my ſelfe but duſte and aſſhes. Bowe to me thyn eare. what ſayſt thou my ſoule? Hath god eares? Thynkeſt thou that he is a bodely thyng? No certenly. For ſythe the ſpirite is farre better than the body, who wolde ſay that god were a body, oneleſſe he
<pb facs="tcp:29051:6"/> be madde? But ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meryng (as well as we may lorde) we ſowne thy celeſtiall and moſte hyghe thynges. we knowe the by thy creatures / we ſpeake to the / &amp; of the by the ſimilitudes of them. Thy eare than what is it lorde? Is it thy knowlege? For by the eares we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande tho thynges, whiche be ſpoken vnto vs. Thou kneweſt from the begynnyng all thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men ſpeake and thynke. May we than vnderſtande by thyn eare thy knowlege? Truely thyn eare doth inſinuate ſome what vnto vs, whiche is not comprehended in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of thy ſimple knowlege. For vnto ſome y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> boweſte thyn eare / vnto other y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> turneſt it awaye. But thy knowlege alwayes abydeth one. what other thyng than is thyn eare / but the notice of thy alowaunce &amp; diſalowaunce. Thou boweſt thyn eare, &amp; heareſt the wordes of good men, bicauſe they pleaſe the, and thou alloweſt them. Contrarywyſe thou turneſt awaye thyn eare from the wordes of the wycked / bicauſe they wyll not departe from theyr wyckednes / therfore the wordes pleaſe the not / but thou diſaloweſt them. what is than to encline thyn eare to them, which ſpeke vnto the / but to alowe theyr prayers, and to beholde them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of pitie and mercy, to enlyghten and kyndle them, that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a truſt &amp; a ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t charite they may pray &amp; deſyre the. For thou wylte gyue them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they aſke hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly. For yf the kynge ſheweth to a poore man, whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to ſpeake with hym, a mery cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and turneth his iyes vnto hym, ſhewy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hym ſelfe redy to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore mannes cauſe / wyll not the poore man be glad? Doth not the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; the attentifenes of the kyng cauſe the poore man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more boldely to ſpeake his mater, and miniſter wordꝭ &amp; eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto hym? yes vndoutedly?
<pb facs="tcp:29051:7"/> So lykewyſe (lorde) we ꝑceyue the, than to bowe thyn eare to our prayers, whan thou graunteſt vs in our prayers, to be ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te in ſpirite. I beſeche the therfore (o mercyful lorde and father) bowe vnto me thyn eare, alowe (I beſeche the) my prayer, enlighten me, kyndle me, and teache me that I ought to axe and deſyre, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and lyfte vp my herte, that at laſte alſo thou mayſte heare my prayer. Haſte the (o mercyfull lorde) to plucke me out, ſhorten the dayes, cutte of the tyme. So bowe vnto me (oh lorde) thyn eare, that ſhortely I may be herde of the. For vnto the, whiche abydeſt for euer, euery tyme is ſhorte. For eternitie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendeth all, and excedeth euery tyme. But vnto me, euery day is longe, for tyme is a numbrynge of the mouynge, ſo that he, which feleth no motion, feleth no tyme, but he that feleth mouynge, feleth tyme / and he moſte of all feleth mouyng, whiche numbreth the partes therof.</p>
            <p>I therfore, whiche numbre the dayes and the houres do moſte of all fele the tyme. And therfore lyke as vnto the a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de yeres are but as yeſterday, that is paſt, ſo vnto me one day is a thouſande yeres, whiche are to come. wherfore haſten the lorde to plucke me out from ſynnes, &amp; myn aduerſaries. For deathe haſteneth and in euery place awayteth for me. Hye the lorde, leſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I preuented of it, haue no ſpace of repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Plucke me out lorde from the hande of the maliciouſe, delyuer me from the bondes of ſunne, take me from the ſnare of death, leade me out of the depnes of helle, ſaue me from oppreſſion, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harde bondage of heuynes, that my mynde may ryſe vp and ioye in the / and that I may blyſſe the all the days of my lyfe. I thanke the lorde in Ieſu my ſauiour, for accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude
<pb facs="tcp:29051:7"/> of my ſorowes in my herte, thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortes haue reioyſed my ſoule. wherfore I wyll alwayes truſte in the / and I wyll for my parte adde vnto all thy prayſe. Thou lord bowe thin eare vnto me, haſten y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to plucke me out. Alas wretche that I am, lo, agayne heuynes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth inſtructed with terrible armours. The banner of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice goeth before her / an innumerable hooſte foloweth her feete / eche hath a ſpere in his hande. I beholde on euery ſyde inſtrumentes of deathe. wo be to me, I am vndone / with an hyghe and horrible voyce ſhe cryeth, O wretche, that ſame thy hope hath deceyued the.</p>
            <p>Lo, thou haſte laboured in vayne, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaydeſt. Bowe thyn eare to me, haſten the to plucke me out. Hath god bowed his eare vnto the? Is thy prayer herde? where is the delyueraunce? where is the conforte? Hath god haſtened to plucke the out? Yet arte thou bounde and a priſoner, nothynge is altered. If thou beleueſt faythe to be trewe, why doeſt onely enbrace hope? Knoweſte thou not that god is iuſte? Knoweſt not his iuſtice?</p>
            <p>He ſpared not his angels / he pitied not them / nor wyll pitie them / but for one only ſynne they be condempned for euermore. Adam ſynned, and the iuſtice of god pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed the whole mankynde with deathe. Thynkeſt that god doth not as wel loue rightwiſenes as mercy? Chyldren deꝑtynge in original ſynne, ſhall neuer ſe the face of god / ſo rygorous is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtice of god, that for the ſynne, whiche they dyd not, but receyued by nature, they ſhall be punyſhed with euerlaſtynge payne. For in helle is no rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption. Knoweſt not that god ſpareth not the offender? Dyd he not deſtroy in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of Noe, almoſte all mankynde? Dyd he not conſume with fyre Sodoma, and the other cities adioynynge vnto it?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29051:8"/>
            <p>Nor the diuine iuſtice hath not ſo moche as taken com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſion of infauntes and innocentes. Howe ofte puny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed he the Iewes offendynge? was not Hieruſalem vtterly deſtroyed by the handes of Nabugodonoſor?</p>
            <p>Neyther ſpared he his owne temple / for it was alſo de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroyed of Titus themperour of Rome / where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iues were ſo cruellye punyſhed / that there is no man that heareth of it, but quaketh for feare. But ſe how ſharpe the iuſtice of god is / the children for the fathers are pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhed euyn to this day. Beholde, the Iues be ſlaues and captiues in euery place / and dyenge in theyr blynd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, are punyſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euerlaſtynge paynes. Troweſte thou the mercye of god is greatter than his iuſtice?</p>
            <p>Truely in god it is neyther greater nor leſſe. For what ſoeuer is in god is his ſubſtaunce. But let vs conſydre the workes of iuſtice &amp; mercy / and we ſhall euidently eſpie, that the workes of iuſtice do excede the workes of mercy. God hym ſelfe is witneſſe, ſayenge: Many be called, fewe elected. Marke howe many infidels be dampned / how many euyl chriſten men there be / howe fewe lyue chriſtianly / and thou ſhalte perceyue anone, that there be farre more veſſels of iuſtice tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mercy. The electe are the veſſels of mercy / the refuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſels of iuſtice. Let not Mary Magdalen make the truſte / nor the thefe / nor Peter / nor Paule / for there was but one Mary / one thefe / one Peter / one Paule. Troweſt thou to be accompted amongeſt ſo fewe? whiche haſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſo many and ſo hughe ſynnes / whiche haſte ben a ſclaunder in the churche / whiche haſte offended heuen and erthe? Lo, thyn iyes hath wepte / thy herte hath beſought mercy / and as yet thou haſte obteyned none. So many prayers of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loued the / be they
<pb facs="tcp:29051:8"/> herde? no, and why ſo? Surely bicauſe thou arte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted amonge the veſſels of yre. Thy hope hath made the to labour in vayne. Folowe my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, heuen hath caſte the vp, the earth receyue the not. who can ſuffre this greate confuſion? Better it is for the to dye, than to lyue / choſe deathe, whiche, yf no man wyll brynge vpon the, lay handes vpon thy ſelfe, ſley thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Theſe wordꝭ ſhe with wonderfull importunitie layde on / and all the whole hooſte with loude voyces dyd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſe the ſame, ſayenge: Deathe onely is thy refuge. But I hearynge this was ſore afrayde, and ſodeynly felle downe vpon my face, cryenge out, and ſayenge: Lorde helpe me, lorde forſake me not, come my hope, come my hope. Lo, ſodeynly hope glyſterynge from heuen came downe, and touched my ſyde, and lifted me vp, and dyd ſet me on my feete, and ſayde: Howe longe yet ſhalte thou be a babe? Howe longe wylte thou be a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouice, and a yonge ſouldier? So ofte thou haſt ben in batayle, and haſte walked in the myddes of the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of deathe, and haſt not yet lerned to fyght? Be thou not diſmayed of the greate iuſtice of god / be thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> fayntherted felowe. Let them feare, whiche be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, whiche walke in theyr owne ways, whiche folowe vanities, whiche knowe not the way of peace. Let the wycked tremble, whiche do gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uouſly ſynne and ſaye, what haue I done? whiche be not conuerted to the herte, whiche be called and refuſe to come / they knowe not god, and wyll not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that they may do well. Let theſe feare. what ſaythe the apoſtle? It is a dredefull thynge to falle in to the handꝭ of the lyuynge god. Suche, doubtles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtice of god punyſheth / ſuche men ꝑteyne to her. But ſynners,
<pb facs="tcp:29051:9"/> whiche returnynge agayne to them ſelues do ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, and runne to the father of mercies, ſayenge: Father,<note place="margin">Luc. xv.</note> I haue ſynned agaynſt heuen &amp; towardes the, but be thou mercyfull vnto me ſynner. Let ſuche haue truſte in the lorde, for he that hath drawen them, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly wyll receyue them &amp; iuſtifie them. Let he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynes brynge forthe, yf ſhe can, one ſynner, were he ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſo greate, whiche conuerted to the lorde, was not receyued of hym, &amp; iuſtified. For although it be writen of Eſau, that he founde no place of repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, though he ſoughte it with teares. This maketh nothynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs / for Eſau dyd not wepe for his ſynnes that he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted / but for his temporall goodes that he had loſte, whiche he coulde not recouer. Nor thynke not that iuſtice doth ſo pertayne to the wycked, that it is clene ſeperate from mercy. Nor agayne that mercy doth ſo belonge to ryghtwyſe men, that it is clene ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from iuſtice. For all the ways of the lorde is mercy and veritie. For he ſheweth mercy alſo to ſinners in gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge them for the good dedes that they do te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porally, temporall rewardes / and after this lyfe in punyſhyng them not ſo moche as they deſerued. Lyke wyſe his electe he purſueth with his iuſtice in punyſhyng them temporally for theyr ſynnes, that they be not punyſhed euerlaſtyngly. Thou therfore ſuffre pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the lorde, thou haſt ſynned, be ſory for it / be content that thrugh his grace thy ſynnes is forgyuen the. My ſonne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not the correction of the lorde / neyther faynt thou whan thou arte checked of hym / for whom the lorde loueth, he chaſtiſeth / he ſcourgeth euery chylde that he receyueth. Continue than in affliction / god ſhewethe hym ſelfe to the, as vnto his ſonne. And though there
<pb facs="tcp:29051:9"/> be fewe choſen chyldren of god, hauynge regarde to the diſalowed, yet there be innumerable that ſhalbe ſaued. Nor there is not only one Mary Magdalen / one thefe / one Peter / one Paule / for innumerable haue folowed theyr ſteppes, doinge penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / and are receyued of the lorde, rewarded with many and great gyftes of grace / nor mercye is no leſſe in her workes, than iuſtice. For mercy gyueth ſo great good thyngꝭ to rightwyſe men, that her workes do farre excede the workes of iuſtice. Knoweſt not that the earthe is ful of the mercy of god? what creature can glorie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath receiued any thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, whiche hath not taken it of the mercy of god? And yf thou haſte greuouſlye offended god, yet his mercye is greater than all the ſinnes of the worlde. Trouble not thy ſelfe for the multitude &amp; greuouſnes of thy ſinnes. Hath not mercy now come re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng &amp; met the? Hath ſhe not taken the vp and kyſſed the? Lo, thou dydeſt falle, and thou werte not hurte. And why ſo? Arte thou not afrayle veſſell, whiche, yf it fall muſte nedes be brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, onles ſome body put vnder his hande? why than whan thou felleſt, werte thou not hurte? who dyd put vnder his hande? who? but the lorde. This is a great ſigne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou arte electe / for the electe whan he falleth, ſhall not be brouſed / for the lorde wyll put vnder his hande. Dothe not the apoſtle write, that to them that loue god, all thynges worke to good? In ſo moche that the very ſynne worketh them to good. Dothe not that falle worke them to good, wherby they be made bothe humbler, and warer. Doth not the lorde receiue hym, whiche is receyued of humilitie? Thou haſt loued the lorde many yeres / for his loue y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte laboured. After thou dydeſt lyfte vp thy herte, and walke in the vanite
<pb facs="tcp:29051:10"/> of thy wytte / the lorde withdrewe his hande, and thou fell / and in to the depnes of the ſee thou dydeſt deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Howe be it the goodnes of the lorde forthwith put vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / and thou werte not brouſed. Say than, whan I was violently ſhoued forthe, I was ouertur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned that I mought fall, and the lorde toke me vp. Not ſo the wycked not ſo / whom god hath reiected. whan they falle they ryſe not agayne / but eyther with greate ſhame they excuſe theyr ſynnes / or elles they haue the boldenes of an harlot / and after they neyther feare god nor man. Aryſe than &amp; be of a ſtronge herte / be myght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and valiaunt / abyde the lorde and do manfully / and let thy herte be enſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthed, and ſuffre the lorde. Thou haſt proued thyn owne proweſſe howe it is of no force. Than humble nowe thy ſelfe vnder the puiſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hande of god / and henſeforth be more ware. Pacience is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to the / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ceaſſynge pray / and the lorde ſhall heare the in due tyme. Aryſe than and lay away al he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines from thy ſelfe / embrace the feete of the lorde, and he ſhall ſaue and delyuer the. Theſe wordes ſayd, ſhe was rauyſhed in to heuen / leauynge me enſtrengthed and wonderfully conforted / whom forthwith with all my herte enſuenge, I ſtode before god. &amp; fallyng downe before my ſauiours feete, I ſayd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a bolde confidence,
<q>¶ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to mihi in deum ꝓtectorem &amp; in domuni retugii vt ſaluum me facias.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶That is to ſay. Be vnto me a god protectour, and an houſe of refuge, that thou mayſt ſaue me.</p>
            <p>¶For thou god arte of all the greateſt and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrongeſt, thou the redemer, &amp; ſauiour of all / thou the ꝓtectour of the faythfull / to the I flee boldely. Hope hath brought me in / hope, whiche thou ſo dearely doſte loue / whom thou haſte alwayes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vnto vs / with her haue
<pb facs="tcp:29051:10"/> I not feared to come before thy face. I graunte I am vnworthy / but ſhe drew me. I feared to approche nere for my manyfolde ſinnes, but ſhe hath encouraged me. Lo, ſhe ſtandethe before the / ſhe beareth wytneſſe / I ſpeake to my lorde, being my ſelfe fleſſhe, and a ſynner / hope taughte me, and ſayd to me, that boldely I ſhuld open my mouthe. Swete and gentle, ꝙ ſhe, is the lord, he wyll not dryue the away / he wyll not be angrye / he wyl gladly heare / what ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> deſireſt he wyl gyue. I beleued / for whiche cauſe I ſpake. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderyng thy maieſtie, I was greately humbled / and I ſayd in my traunce / euery man is a lyar / I wyll neuer more truſte in man, but in the onely / thou onely arte faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all thy wordes / and euery man is a lyar. what ſhall I yelde the, oh lorde, for all that thou haſt gyuen vnto me? The cuppe of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wyll take / for from henſeforthe I wyll lyue not vnto me, but vnto the / do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge good for thy loue / I wyll ſuffre all euyls / I wyll not do this thrugh myn owne myghte / but I wyll call on the name of the lorde. My vowes I wyll yelde to all thy people. For in the ſyght of god the deathe of his ſayntes is precious. Be than vnto me a god ꝓtectour, defende me from myn enemies. Myn enemies are my ſynnes, whiche ꝓuoke thy ryghtwyſenes agaynſt me. I ſhall not be able to ſtande agaynſt them / yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doſt not protecte me. Let thy mercy be my ſhylde lorde, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſhylde of thy good wyll crowne me. I haue nothing to offre vnto him, wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre his furour, al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I bryng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me accuſe me. wherfore I wyl offre thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion lorde. Be not diſpleaſed lord god, but rather be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me god ꝓtectour, vnder thy wyngꝭ ꝓtecte me, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſhulders ſhadow me / &amp; vnder thy fethers I wyl truſt.
<pb facs="tcp:29051:11"/> what ſhal iuſtice do to me, if thou kepeſt me vnder thy protection? She wyll holde her peace lorde, and put vp the ſwerde of her furie / ſhe ſhall be made tame and gentle, ſeinge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes of thy incarnation / beholdyng the woundes of thy paſſion / conſyderyng the bloude of thy charitie / ſhe wyll departe fro me, &amp; ſay: Be mery ſonne thou haſte founde me / eate in peace / ſlepe &amp; reſte together with me. Be therfore lorde to me a god, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour, an houſe of refuge, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of rayne and ſtorme, in tyme of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations, I may flee vnto the / for in the onely is my helth / be thou vnto me a houſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge / open vnto me thy ſyde perſed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpeare, that I may entre the breſte of ſo tender loue / in whiche I may be ſafe from the feblenes of ſpirite, &amp; from te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt / hyde me in thy tabernacle / in the day of euyls protecte me in an angle of thy tabernacle / let it be the houſe of my refuge, that thou mayſte make me ſafe / for I can not be but ſafe in the houſe of thy refuge / for thou haſt put thy refuge moſte hyghe / this place is well fenſed / no enemyes is there feared / wolde god I myghte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways abyde in it / who dwelleth in it can not be woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. wherfore at all temptations, at all tribulations, at all neceſſities, open lorde vnto me the houſe of thy refuge / ſpreade abrode the boſome of thy tender loue / ſhewe forthe the bowels of thy mercy / that thou mayſt make me ſafe / let not the tempter come thyther / let not the ſclaunderer clyme vp / let not that noughtie accuſer of his brethern approche / I ſhalbe than ſure without cure / yea alredye me thynketh I am excedyngly well and quiete. I thanke the good Ieſu, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſente thy hope vnto me / whiche hath rayſed me of duſte and of donge, lyfte me vp, and ſet me before the, that thou
<pb facs="tcp:29051:11"/> ſhuldeſt be god, my protectour, and the houſe of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, to thentent thou ſhuldeſt ſaue me. My mynde is troubled: Lo, heuynes is at hande, ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth with the banner of iuſtice / from yeſterdays conflicte / ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth not / but ſhe is defended with other weapons / for this nyghte ſhe hath ſtolen away my weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / and with my ſwerdꝭ ſhe hath gyrded her ſouldiers. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnweapened &amp; weyke, what ſhall I do? Lo howe bytterly ſhe cryethe / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what aſſaute ſhe ſetteth vpon me / what a truſt ſhe hath of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victorie. where, ꝙ ſhe, is thy protectour? where is thy houſe of refuge? wher is thy helthe? Continueſt ſtyll in thy vayne hope? Thy confortes procede but of imagination. Thou ymagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt god mercyfull / and thy protectour / and the houſe of thy refuge / and thou thynkeſt thou clymmeſt vp to heuen. Surely thou arte illuded of thy fantaſye / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted with vayne hope. Thynkeſt that thou werte rauiſhed vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrd heuen? Theſe are but dreames, Recou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te with thy ſelfe howe greuous an offence is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude. Doth not this drye vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayn of mercy? Remembre, Chriſte wepte for the citie of Hieruſalem / and tolde afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euyls that ſhulde fall vpon it, ſayeng: The days ſhall come vpon the / and thyn enemies ſhall beſege the, and compaſſe the aboute / and dryue the in to ſtreytes / and beate the downe to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / and thy chyldren that be in the / and they ſhall not leaue in the a ſtone vpon a ſtone. Nor the cauſe of ſo greate venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce he kepte not cloſe, but added it, ſayeng: Bicauſe thou kneweſt not the tyme of thy viſitation. Lo, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude deſerueth not only to be depriued of benefitꝭ, but alſo greuouſly to be punyſhed. Dothe not this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe to the ſoule? Dothe not Hieruſalem often tymes
<pb facs="tcp:29051:12"/> in ſcripture ſignifieth the ſoule? whiche whan it wyll not knowe the viſitation of the lorde, is beſeged with dyuels, and with ſondry temptations, wherwith it is afflicte, falleth downe to earthly thingꝭ, is ꝓſtrate, nor no good vertue, nor no good dede is lefte in it, whiche is not deſtroyed, for it is ſpoyled of all grace / neyther is it buylded agayne, ſhe knoweth not the tyme of her vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation. Thou, truely, thou, I ſay, arte this citie, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryched of god with many &amp; greate benefites, and thou acknowlegeſt it not, but werte vnkynde / he created the to his owne lykelynes / in myddes of his churche, not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the infidels he made the to be borne / he dyd ſet the in a floryſhy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g citie / with the water of baptiſme he ſanctified the / in a religious houſe he brought the vp. But thou ranneſt after thy luſtes, in the vanitie of thy brayne thou walkedeſt / thou ranneſt downe in to depe ſynnes / the lorde called the, and thou anſweredeſt not. He ofte aduertiſed the, and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> regardedſt not his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell. Howe ofte dyd he lyghten the? Howe ofte dyd he turne the to thy herte? How ofte dyd he awake the fro ſlepe? He inuited the, and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> excuſedeſt thy ſelfe / he plucked, and thou dydeſt reſyſt hym. At laſt his ineffable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ouercome the. Thou dydeſt offende, and he viſited the / thou felleſt, and he plucte the vp / thou werte igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, and he taughte the / thou werte blynde, and he lyghtned the / from the rumble of the worlde / from the tempeſt of the ſee, he broughte the to quietenes, and to the porte of religion / he gaue the the habite of holy con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſation / he made the his preeſte / he brought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to the ſcholes of his wyſedome / and yet thou haſte alwayes ben vnkynde / and negligently thou haſt done the wyll of the lorde / whan yet thou kneweſt it wryten. Curſed
<pb facs="tcp:29051:12"/> is he that dothe the worke of the lorde neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. Nor thus the goodnes of god dyd not leaue the, but alwaye broughte the gently to better / and whiche is moſte of all, garnyſhed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with knowlege of ſcripture, the worde of preachynge he put in thy mouthe / and dyd ſet the in the myddes of his people, as one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate &amp; famous men. Thou, this notwithſtandyng, taughteſte other, and regardeſt not thy ſelfe / other thou healedeſt, &amp; thy ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſauedeſte not / thou lyftedeſt vp thy herte in thy worſhyp / and therfore thou haſt loſte thy wyſedome in thy worſhyp. Nought werte thou made, and nought ſhalte thou be for euermore. Knoweſte thou not that the ſeruaunt knowyng the wyll of the lorde, and doing it not, ſhalbe beaten w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many ſtrypes? Doſt not knowe that god reſiſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proude? Howe felleſt thou Lucifer / whiche dydeſt ſpring vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornyng / whiche dydeſt wounde the gentyls / whiche ſaydeſte in thy herte, I wyll clym vp to heuen. But y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> werte plucked downe, to helle in to the depe of the lake / vnder the lyethe the mottes / and thy hyllyng is wormes. Thynkeſt thou nowe to fynde mercye, whiche haſte offended many / whiche ſo ofte called and monyſhed of god, woldeſt not anſwere? where were than the iuſtice of god? where were than the equitie of iudgement? Mercy doth not alway folowe ſynners / ſhe hath ſet her boundes. Is it not wryten: I haue called, and ye haue becked away / I haue ſpred abrode my handes, and there was none that wolde loke vpon me / ye haue deſpiſed my counſel, and neglected my increpations: I alſo in your decaye wyll laughe and ieſte, whan that thynge that ye fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red come vnto you?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29051:13"/>
            <p>Lo, not alwayes mercy gyueth pardone to the ſynner. Doeſt not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degrees of mercy to haue an ende / in the whiche, being adourned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo many benefites of god, dydeſt fall into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe ſee / whiche garniſhed with ſo many graces / for thy pryde and vayneglory werte a ſclaunder to the worlde? Let not than vayne hope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the, whom thou foloweſt / lyue henſeforth after thy luſte &amp; appetite / be not punyſhed bothe in this lyfe and in the other with eternall paynes. Choſe to dwell with them, whiche leade theyr dayes in pleaſure, and in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t go downe to helle. Nor let not ſhame holde the backe. Take the foreheed of an harlot / let vs eate and drynke for to morowe ſhall we dye. Thy wounde is deſpayred on, it is made incurable. whan ſhe had ſayde theſe wordes, all the hooſte cryed out with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible voyces, and repeted her wordes, ſayenge: Thy wounde is deſpayred on, and made vncurable.</p>
            <p>¶I remembryng the aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of my mother, thoughe I was ſomwhat deiecte in mynde, yet to my power I plucked vp my ſelfe, and ſtode vpon my feete, lyftynge vp myn iyes to heuen, from whens I hoped for helpe. And lo, hope with a cherefull countenaunce furnyſhed with diuine beames, deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng from aboue ſayde, who is that that enuolueth ſentences with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerned wordꝭ, which ſetteth bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to infinite mercy? whiche folyſhe perſone thinkeſt to beare the waters of the ſee in her handꝭ. Haſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not herde the lorde, ſayeng: In what houre ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinner bewayleth his ſinnes, none of all his inquities I wyll recorde? what man is he that ſynneth not? who can ſaye my herte is clene? The Pater noſter belongeth to all, in whiche all men are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to ſay: Dimitte nobis debita noſtra. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue
<pb facs="tcp:29051:13"/> vs our ſinnes. Our lorde taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles thus to praye. Dothe not than this prayer belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to other? Thapoſtles receyued fyrſte the holy ghoſte. And why taughte he them thus to praye, yf they had no ſynne / and yf they had, who can glorifie that he is no ſynner? Heare the beloued diſciple of the lord. Yf we ſay, ꝙ he, that we haue no ſinnes, we begyle our ſelues, &amp; trouth is not in vs. Iames the apoſtle. In many thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gꝭ, ꝙ he, we all offende. wherfore all haue ſynned, and nede the mercy of god, yea the holy men of god. For it is writen, Seuen tymes a day fall the iuſte man, and he ſhal ryſe agayne. wherfore mercy hath no limittes nor bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. But ſo ofte as the ſynner lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth his gylte, ſo ofte he obteyneth mercye. Nor it ſkillethe not whether we ſpeake of greate or of lytle offences. Thou haſt fallen, aryſe, and mercye ſhall take the vp. Thou ſhrynkeſt, calle, and mercy ſhall come vnto the. Agayne thou fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſte, agayne thou ſhrynkeſte / turne the to the lorde, and the bowelles of his pitie ſhall open to the. Thou fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſte the thyrde tyme, and the fourthe. Knocke, crye, and mercye wyll not forſake the. As ofte as thou ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, ſo ofte ryſe agayne, &amp; mercy ſhall haue none ende. why doſt thou vpbrayde the benefites that thou haſte taken, o thou wretched woman, heuynes? Dyd not Dauid the greate prophete receyue many &amp; greate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites? Of whom the lorde ſayde, I haue founde a man accordynge to my herte: and yet he ſynned, &amp; that greuouſly, as well in aduoutrie, as in the murderyng of a good and innocent perſone / and yet the lorde ended not his mercy in hym. what bryngeſt thou the ſynne of pryde? Dyd not Dauid lyfte vp his herte, &amp; cauſed to nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre the people of Iſrael? For he gloried as though
<pb facs="tcp:29051:14"/> he had ben a greate kynge and a myghtye in his owne ſtrengthe and puiſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / and yet he was not reiecte for this. why? For he dyd not hyde his ſyn, he dyd not boſt it as Sodoma dyd, but he ſayd: I wyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe agay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt my ſelfe, myn iniuſtice to the lorde. wherfore mercye hath ſet no limites nor boundes vnto her ſelfe / but the wicked &amp; dampned ꝑſones do ſet endes to them ſelues, that they may not paſſe vnto it, for ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to them but they dryue her away. wherfore it is writen: Thy perdition Iſrael is of thy ſelfe / of me only is thy helpe. Open thy mouthe, ſaythe mercy, and I wyll fylle it. Holde out thy boſome, &amp; I wyll gyue the a good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and heaped full, and flowynge ouer. Continue in prayers and wepynge. For he that hath begon to loue the, and prouoke the with benefites and graces to his loue, wyl not leaue the, but gyue the encreaſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme rather his worke. what naturall cauſe begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth a worke, &amp; leaueth in the myd way? The vertue of ſede ceaſſeth not vntyll it hath broughte the frute to perfection. what byrde leaueth her yonge, before they be able to rule them ſelues? why do they this? what profite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vnto them of this? None truelye but onely labour. Loue than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelleth the natural cauſes to brynge theyr effectes to ꝑfection / goodnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelleth them, whiche they couet to poure out / for goodnes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes diffundeth it ſelfe. If than the creatures do this, what ſhall the creator do? for he is the ſelfe loue, he is infinite goodnes. Shall not he make ꝑfecte his worke? Heare the lorde Ieſus, It is my worke, ꝙ he, to do the wyll of hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſente me, that I ſhulde make perfecte his worke. He than y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> began to loue the, with his giftes and free benefites to allure the vnto hym, to
<pb facs="tcp:29051:14"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>enſe the, and alſo to pourge the from ſynne. without doubte he wyll make perfecte his worke / for theſe be the preparations of euerlaſtynge lyfe. why therfore nowe whan thou felleſt, werte thou not brouſed? was it not bicauſe the lorde dyd put vnder his hande? And why dyd he put vnder his hande? why dyd he turne to the thy herte? why dyd he prouoke the to repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? why dyd he conforte the? was it not bicauſe he wolde make the cleaue &amp; ſticke vnto hym, and make the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy his grace, &amp; brynge the to euerlaſtyng lyfe? Theſe be not illuſions, and thy imaginations / but diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations. But be it, let them be imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, be they not good? Do they not come from the vertue of fayth? wherfore ſyth all good iſſueth from god, vndoubtedly theſe imaginations are diuine illuminations. Reioyſe therfore in theſe wordes. At theſe wordes my herte was ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, that for ioye I began to ſyng, ſayeng.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Dominus illuminatio mea: et ſalus mea / quem timebo?</p>
               <p>Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s protector vite mee: a quo trepidabo?</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶That is to ſay: The lorde is myn enlyghtnyng and my helthe, whom ſhall I feare?</p>
            <p>¶The lorde is the ꝓtectour of my lyfe, of whom ſhall I be abaſhed?</p>
            <p>¶At the feete of the lorde proſtrate with wepynge I ſayd, Lorde, though a felde be pytched agaynſt me, my herte ſhall not feare / for my fortitude, &amp; my refuge arte thou / and for thy names ſake thou ſhalte bryng me out and nouryſhe me.</p>
            <p>¶An ende of the exſpoſition of Hierome of Ferrarie vpon the pſalme of In te domine ſperaui, whiche preuented by deathe he coulde not fynyſhe.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:29051:15"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29051:15"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Mens cujusque is est Quisque</head>
                  <p>SP</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
